Osip Mandelʹshtam Papers, 1900s-1970s (bulk 1914-1937 ): Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
- "Kiev" (parts II and I), 1926 May 27; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  Essay/memoir, handwritten copy of printed text (published 1926 May 27), in hand of NM and E. Ia. Khazin (pp.3-4); for fragments of author's draft manuscript see Box 1, Folder 13
- "Mikhoels", 1926; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  Article, handwritten copy of newspaper text (published 1926), in hand of NM; for fragments of author's draft manuscript see Box 1, Folder 25
- "Zhak rodilsia i umer", 1929; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  Article, handwritten copy of newspaper text (published 1929), in hand of NM; on obverse of p.1: p. 4 of NM's copy of "Literaturnaia Moskva" (the rest of that copy in Box 2, Folder 4)
- "Literaturnaia Moskva: rozhdenie fabuly": article, handwritten copy of newspaper text (published 1922), in hand of NM, 1 folder (Folder 8)
- "Pis'mo o russkoi poezii": article, handwritten copy of newspaper text (published 1922), in hand of NM, 1 folder (Folder 9)
- "Batum": article, handwritten copy of newspaper text (published 1922), pp.1-3 in hand of E. Ia Khazin, pp.3-5 in hand of NM, 1 folder (Folder 10)
- "Gruziia" (title on cover in NM's hand), 1922; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  Article, handwritten copy of newspaper text (published 1922 as "Koe-chto o gruzinskom iskusstve"), in hand of E. Ia Khazin; for fragments of original typescript see B2 F11
- Two articles: handwritten copies (1922-1923), undated; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  1. ["Krovavaia misteriia 9-go ianvaria"]: newspaper article, fragments of handwritten copy of printed text (published 1922), in hand of E. Ia. Khazin; for fragments of typescript see Box 1, Folder 20 -- 2. ["Armiia poetov," part 1]: magazine article, fragments of handwritten copy of printed text (published 1923), in hand of NM; for typescript see Box 1, Folder 26
- "Fransua Villon": article on François Villon, fragments of author's final manuscript, tiltle on cover in hand of N. I. Khardzhiev, 1912-1913; 1 folder (Folder 13)
- "Retsenziia na knigu Zhana-Rishara Blokha", 1930s; 1 folder (Folder 14)
  Book review, one of so-called "inner reviews," evaluation of Jean Richard Bloch's Destin du siècle for Zemlia i Fabrika publishing house, original typescript on publisher's form
- "Retsenziia na knigu Zh. Diuamelia", 1930s; 1 folder (Folder 15)
  Book review ("inner review"), evaluation of Georges Duhamel's Géographie cordiale de l'Europe, original typescript on publisher's form
- "Retsenziia na knigu Abelia Armana": book review ("inner review"), evaluation of Abel Arman's Sceptre, handwriten copy, in hand of NM, 1930s; 1 folder (Folder 16)
- [...Vnimanie! Doblest' liricheskogo poeta!...]: loose unidentified fragment (title on cover in hand of NM), in hand of NM, undated; 1 folder (Folder 17)
- "Koe-chto o gruzinskom iskusstve": article, fragments of typescript, 1922; 1 folder (Folder 18)
- Article; unidentified outline (1928-1930), undated; 1 folder (Folder 19)
  1. "O detskoi literature": article (unfinished), handwritten manuscript in hand of NM, draft in hand of NM, 1928-1930 on pp.3 and 4 of draft manuscript -- 2. [Outline of a filmscript?]: unidentified fragment, in hand of NM
- [ Puteshestvie v Armeniiu]: an essay, transcribed fragments of author's notebook entriesin hand of D.Borisov (1931-1932), undated; 1 folder (Folder 20)
  fragment 1: ["Pallas"], for original see Box 4, Folder 26 (envelope 1) -- fragment 2: ["Sukhum"], for original see Box 4, Folder 23 (envelope 20)
- Razgovor o Dante: literary criticism, book (1930-1933), undated; 1 folder (Folder 21)
  I. drafts and notes (collated fragments in numbered envelopes), some in hand of OM, some in hand of NM, two sheets of typed manuscript, fragment of Dante's Commedia Divina copied (in Italian) in hand of OM (title on cover for that fragment in hand of N. Khardzhiev) -- II. complete handwritten copy of final version in hand of NM
- "Novye stikhi", undated; 1 folder (Folder 22)
  Collection of poems, poems 1930-34, author's manuscripts, drafts and fragments, copies made by NM and others; collated items in individual envelopes, item numbering below follows that of I. Semenko's on covers (1918-1934 April)
  1. Kuda kak strashno nam s toboi..., no. 202: I. copy in hand of NM made in OM's lifetimeII. copy in hand of NM made in OM's lifetimeIII. typewritten copy -- 2. Ia tebia nikogda ne uvizhu..., no. 184: final manuscript in hand of NM, date in hand of OM3. Ty krasok sebe pozhelala..., no. 205: I. "Lomaetsia mel i kroshitsia...," early variant (first two stanzas later replaced), copy in hand of NM (green ink), corrections, stanzas in margins, and date in hand of OM (pencil); verso: two lines and 1 stanza in OM's handII. "Lomaetsia mel i kroshitsia...", early variant, typescript, 14 variants in margins in hand of OM (green ink)III. "Ty krasok sebe pozhelala...," final version, copy in hand of NM4: I. "Lomaetsia mel i kroshitsia...," early variant, typescript with stanzas in margins in hand of NMII. [ Ty krasok sebe pozhelala...], no. 205: early variant ("Lomaetsia mel i kroshitsia..."), typescript, stanzas in margin in hand of NM; (on obverse of III)III. Dorogaia, dorogaia, dorogaia..., draft of stanza in hand of OM -- 5. Akh, nichego ia ne vizhu..., no. 296, final manuscript in hand of NM, date in hand of OM, verso: "Vspomni detskii cernil'nyi penal...," 1 stanza in hand of NM6. Kakaia roskosh v nishchenskom selen'i..., no. 213: I. author's draft, includes canceled stanza ("Zapriazhka bykov...")II. final manuscript in hand of NM, date in hand of OM -- 7. Zakutav rot, kak vlazhnuiu rozu..., no. 207: final manuscript, first stanza in hand of NM, second stanza and date in hand of OM8. [Dikaia koshka -- armianskaia rech...], no. 218: I. early variant of two stanzas: stanza 3 "Grianulo v dveri znakomoe: ba!...", stanza 4 "A ne pora l' ochutitsia mne tam..." (crossed out): author's draft; on obverse: notes to Puteshestvie v Armeniiu, in hand of NMII. early variant of two stanzas: stanza 3 as stanza 5 of no. 247, stanza 4 "I po-zverinomu voet liud'e..." (no. 220), both crossed out: author's draft; on obverse: OM's notes made in Tiflis archives; stanza 6 of no. 247 ("Byli my liudi, a stali liud'e...), in hand of NM -- 9. I po-zverinomu voet liud'e..., no. 220, typed manuscript -- 10. Orushchikh kamnei gosudarstvo..., no. 179, author's manuscript11. Koliuchaia rech araratskoi doliny..., no. 216: I. author's manuscriptII. author's draft -- 12. Ne razvaliny -- net -- no porubka moguchego tsirkul'nogo lesa..., no. 210: author's draft -- 13. Ruku platkom obmotai i v ventsenosnyi shipovnik... no. 178: author's draft, first 12 lines ("Ty tol'ko posmotri na armianskie kladbishcha...") not included in final version -- 14. Kholodno roze v snegu..., no. 221: author's manuscript -- 15Note: See item 38 of this folder -- 16. Posle polunochi serdtse voruet..., no. 195: author's manuscript17. Ia skazhu tebe s poslednei priamotoi..., no. 226: I. final manuscript in hand of NM, OM's note in pencil on bottom: "For ‘Leningrad’.."II. final manuscript in hand of NM18-19. two poems not separated, both author's draft: I. Za gremuchuiu doblest' griadushchikh vekov..., no. 227II. Net, ne spriatatsia mne ot velikoi mury..., no. 23220. Koliut resnitsy. V grudi prikipela sleza..., no. 229: I. typed manuscriptII. author's manuscript, on obverse: stanza "Uvedi menia v noch, gde techet Enisei...," author's manuscriptIII. Za gremuchuiu doblest' griadushchikh vekov..., no. 227, author's manuscript, Mar., fourth stanza corrected in red ink Koliut resnitsy..., author's manuscript, 1931 March(on same sheet as III)[ Puteshestvie v Armeniiu]: fragment of author's manuscript (on reverse)21. Zhil Aleksandr Gertsovich..., no. 228: I. final manuscript in hand of NM (pencil), corrections in hand of OM (ink)II. author's manuscript with corrections, without last stanza of final versionIII. typescript with OM's corrections22. Ia s dymiashchei luchinoi vkhozhu..., no. 231: I. final manuscript in hand of NM, date in hand of OMII. final manuscript in hand of NM -- 23. Roial' ( Kak parlament, zhuiushchii frondu...), no. 234: final manuscript in NM's hand24-25: I. Sokhrani moiu rech navsegda...( A. A. A.), no. 235: author's manuscipt on obverse of second sheetII. Net, ne migren', no podai karandashik mentolovyi, no. 285: author's draft26. Kantsona ( Neuzheli ia uvizhu zavtra...), no. 236: I. typescript with OM's correctionsII. final manuscript in hand of NM (pencil), corrections in hand of OM (ink)III. final manuscript in hand of NM, slightly different version -- 27. Dovol'no kuksit'sia! Bumagi v stol zasunem..., no. 247: early version, manuscript in hand of NM, later corrections in hand of OM -- 28. [ Tam, gde kupalni-bumagopriadil'ni...], no. 224: author's draft of third stanza ("U reki Oki vyvernuto veko...") -- 29. [ Lamark ( Byl starik, zastenchivyi kak mal'chik...)], no. 254: manuscript in hand of NM, last three stanzas ("On skazal: dovol'no polnozvuchia..."), last two lines different from final version30-31: I. Kogda v dalekuiu Koreiu..., no. 255: two copies of final manuscript in hand of NM; on obverse of second sheetII. Noch na dvore. Barskaia lzha..., no. 230: manuscript in hand of NM notes in brackets on both in hand of N. Khardzhiev32-33. Novellino ( Vy pomnite, kak beguny...), no. 256: I. Florentiitsy: first two stanzas of no. 256, manuscript in hand of NMII. "Uvy, rastaiala svecha...": stanzas 3-6 of no. 256, manuscript in hand of NMIII. complete typescript -- 34. Impressionizm (Khudozhnik nam izobrazil...), no. 258: manuscript in hand of NM35. Daite Tiutchevu strekozu..., no. 259: I. author's manuscript, one line in margins in hand of NMII. manuscript in hand of NM36-37. Stikhi o russkoi poezii, no. 233-235: I. Zashumela, zadrozhala..., no. 263: author's manuscriptII. "Grom zhivet svoim nakatom...": [stanzas 3 and 4 of no. 233 ( Siad', Derzhavin, razvalis'...)], stanza 3 in hand of NM, stanza 4 in hand of OMIII-IV. Zashumela, zadrozhala..., no. 263: two sheets of typescript with corrections in hand of OM, first sheet: stanzas 1-2, second sheet: stanzas 3-4V-VI. Poliubil ia les prekrasnyi..., no. 264: author's draft; on obverse: Roial'( Kak parlament, zhuiushchii frondu...), no. 234: typescriptVII. Zashumela, zadrozhala..., no. 263: author's manuscriptVIII-IX. "Katit grom svoiu telezhku...": stanzas 2-4 of no. 234, manuscript in hand of NM, corrections; (on same sheet as Poliubil ia les prekrasnyi... ),)Poliubil ia les prekrasnyi..., stanzas 1-4 of no. 235, manuscript in hand of NM "Tychut shpagami shishigi...": stanzas 5-8 of no. 235: typescript with NM's corrections; (list of poem titles in list of poem titles in Armeniia cycle on reverse)List of poem titles in list of poem titles in Armeniia cycle38. (also 15.) K nemetskoi rechi ( Sebia gubia, sebe protivorecha...), no. 266: I. "Vospominanii vozdukh shokoladnyi...": early variant of 266, author's draft manuscript of three stanzas, one on obverseII. "Kogda pylaiut veimarskie svechi...": variant of first six stanzas of 266, manuscript in hand of NM, corrections in hand of OMIII. K nemetskoi rechi ( Sebia gubia, sebe protivorecha...), with dedication to B. S. Kuzin, copy in hand of NMIV. K nemetskoi rechi ( Sebia gubia, sebe protivorecha...), typescript, of first four stanzas, corrections in hand of NMV. Khristian Kleist ( Est' mezhdu nami pokhvala bez lesti...), variant of 266, dictated by OM to A. V. Zvenigorodskii, (NM's biographical note on top)VI. Rhyming scheme and date: 1932 August 8, in hand of OMVII. Khristian Kleist ( Est' mezhdu nami pokhvala bez lesti...), variant of 266, author's draft manuscript, cut in two parts;on obverse: item 15: Ia vernulsia v moi gorod, znakomyi do slez..., no. 221: typescript -- 39. Kogda, unichtozhiv nabrosok..., no. 250: typewritten copy -- 40. I Shubert na vode, i Motsart v ptichem game..., no. 281, typewritten copy41. Kak solovei sirotstvuiushchii slavit..., no. 487: I. "Kak solovei svoe neschastie slavit...": variant of no. 487, first two stanzas in hand of NM, epigraph from Petrarch and the rest of poem in hand of OMII. author's manuscript of final version, 1933 December; on obverse: three last lines of Na strashnoi vysote bluzhdaiushchii ogon'..., no. 101: typescript, punctuation different from final version, 191842. Rechka raspukhshaia ot slez solenykh..., no. 488: I. author's draft manuscript;, undated; on obverse: Cherepakha ( Na kamennykh otrogakh Pierii...), no. 105, typescript, 1919II. copy in hand of E. Ia. Khazin, epigraph and correction in hand of OMIII. Kak solovei sirotstvuiushchii slavit..., no. 487: incomplete copy in hand of E. Ia. Khazin, epigraph in hand of OMNote: (On same sheet as II)43. Promchalis' dni moi, kak by olenei..., no. 490: I. manuscript in hand of NM, epigraph, corrections in hand of OMII. author's final manuscript with numerous corrections, note on bottom in OM's hand"Completed after receiving news of the death of B. N. Bugaev" -- 44. Kogda usnet zemlia i zhar otpyshet..., no. 489: author's draft manuscript45-48. [ A. Belomu]: I-III on one sheet, all in hand of E. Ia. KhazinI. 10 ianvaria 1934 g. ( Menia presleduiut dve-tri sluchainykh frazy...), no. 289II. On dirizhiroval kavkazskimi gorami..., no. 262III. Kogda dushe i toropkoi i robkoi..., no. 291, continued in item IV on next sheetIV. "...Zastenchivost'iu slavnoi novichka...," continued from above, in hand of E. Ia. KhazinV. Golubye glaza i goriachaia lobnaia kost'..., no. 288: copy in hand of NM (ink), corrections and date in hand of OM (pencil)VI. ( Menia presleduiut dve-tri sluchainykh frazy...), no. 289:, copy in hand of L. N. Gumilev (ink), corrections in hand of OMVII. A posredi tolpy -- zadumchivyi, bradatyi..., no. 290: copy in hand of NM, (I. Semenko suggests that the copy was made around 1937)VIII. Otkuda privezli? Kogo? Kotoryi umer?... no. 263: copy in hand of NMIX-XVI. all on one sheet, all in hand of NMIX-XV: Golubye glaza i goriachaia lobnaia kost'..., no. 288; 10 ianvaria 1934 g. ( Menia presleduiut dve-tri sluchainykh frazy...), no. 289; Kogda dushe i toropkoi i robkoi..., no. 291; "Dyshali shub mekha..." (last three stanzas of no. 289), On dirizhiroval kavkazskimi gorami..., no. 293XI. Masteritsa vinovatykh vzorov..., no. 295 -- 49. Fragment of lost poem recorded by memory by NM ( V otsinkovannom vlazhnom Batume...), no. 523
- "Voronezhskie tetradi"; [addition to archive] (undated), 1 folder (Folder 23)
  Collected manuscripts of poems, poem drafts and fragments; collated items in individual envelopes, description on each cover, items in hand of OM, NM, E. Ia. Khazin, N. Shtempel', L. N. Gumilev, also typewritten; many items bear pencil marks in < > brackets signed N. Kh. (Nikolai Khardzhiev); I. Semenko's item numbering continues from previous folder (" Novye stikhi"). Items 50-122: "Voronezhskie tetradi": poems written in exile in Voronezh (1935-1937): 50. Chernozem ( Pereuvazhena, perecherna, vsia v khole...), no. 299 (1935 April). I. author's final manuscript (undated). II. author's final manuscript (1935 April). III. Esli by povedal Bog..., no. ?, copy in hand of NM, undated (on reverse of II) (undated) -- 51. Ia zhivu na vazhnykh ogorodakh..., no. 353: typewritten (undated) -- 52. Den' stoial o piati golovakh..., no. 313 (1935 April-May). I. author's manuscript of early (shorter) version (1935 April-May). II. typescript, same version and date (undated). III. typed copy of last three stanzas as given in no. 315, made by I. Semenko in late 1940s (her note) (undated) -- 53-53a. Da, ia lezhu v zemle, gubami shevelia..., no. 306 (1935 May). I. "Tam degot' progudel, lazur'iu shevelia...": variant of first two stanzas of no. 306: author's manuscript (1935 May). II. same text as above: author's manuscript (1935 May ). III. complete text as given in no. 327: typescript (1935 May) -- 54. Eshche my zhizn'iu polny v vysshei mere, no. 302: copy in hand of NM, made in 1937 (undated) -- 55. [Kama], no. 308-310 (undated). I. Kak na Kame-reke glazu temno, kogda..., no. 309: variant, author's manuscript (undated). II. Ia smotrel, otdaliaias' na khvoinyi vostok..., no. 310: author's manuscript; (III and IV on reverse of sheet with I and II) (undated). III. Lishiv menia morei, razbega i razleta..., no. 307: copy in hand of NM (undated). IV. "...mne skazhet: nichego, otets...", fragment in hand of NM (undated). V. Kak na Kame-reke..., no. 308: author's draft of uncensored variant of last two stanzas (undated) -- 56. Stansy ( Ia ne khochu sred' iunoshei teplichnykh...), no. 312 (1935 May). I. copy in hand of NM (undated). II. "Prokliatyi shov, nelepaia zateia...", variant (no first stanza, other stanzas in different order): copy in hand of NM (1935 May). III. "Liubliu shinel' krasnoarmeiskoi skladki...", variant of stanza: two typed copies, one copy in hand of NM (undated) -- 57. Ot syroi prostyni govoriashchaia, no. 311: copy in hand of NM (undated) -- 58. Vozmozhna li zhenshchine mertvoi khvala?..., no. 314: copy in hand of N. Shtempel', date in hand of OM (1935 June 3-1926 December 14) -- 59. Rimskikh nochei polnovesnye slitki..., no. 316: copy in hand of NM (undated) -- 60. Za Paganini dlinnopalym..., no. 298: copy in hand of N. Shtempel', date in hand of OM (1935 summer) -- 61. Iz-za domov, iz-za lesov..., no. 322 (1926 December 6-9). I. copy in hand of NM, date in hand of OM (1926 December 6-9). II. copy and date in hand of NM (1926 December 6-8). III. typed copy, slightly different version (undated) -- 62. Rozhdenie ulybki ( Kogda zaulybaetsia ditia...), no. 342 (1926 December 8-1937 January 17). I. copy in hand of NM, date in hand of OM (1926 December 9-1937 January 6). II. copy and date in hand of NM (1926 December 8-1937 January 17). III. copy in hand of NM, date in hand of OM (1926 December 8-1937 January 9). IV. copy in hand of NM, date in hand of OM (1926 December 9-11). V. copy in hand of NM (undated) -- 63 (1926 December). I. Moi shchegol, ia golovu zakinu..., no. 324: copy in hand of NM (1926 December 10-27). II. Detskii rot zhuet svoiu miakinu..., no. 326, variant of no. 324: copy in hand of NM, date in hand of OM (1926 December 9-13). III. Detskii rot zhuet svoiu miakinu..., no. 326: copy in hand of NM, date in hand of OM (1926 December) -- 64. Nynche den' kakoi-to zheltorotyi..., no. 294: copy in hand of NM (1926 December 9-28) -- 65. Ne u menia, ne u tebia -- u nikh..., no. 328 (1926 December 9-27). I. copy in hand of NM (1926 December 9-27). II. shorter variant, copy in hand of NM (1926 December 11) -- 66. Ia v serdtse veka -- put' neiasen..., no. 332 (1926 December). I. copy in hand of NM, inscription on top and bottom in hand of OM (1926 December). II. copy in hand of NM (1926 December 14) -- 67. Vnutri gory bezdeistvuet kumir..., no. 330 (1926 December). I. manuscript in hand of NM, corrections and date in hand of OM (1926 December 10-26). II. manuscript in hand of NM, corrections and date in hand of OM (1926 December 13). III. manuscript in hand of NM, corrections and date in hand of OM (1926 December). IV. copy (final version) in hand of NM (1926 December 10-26) -- 68 (1926 December). I. Plastinkoi tonen'koi zhilleta..., no. 334: copy in hand of NM, date in hand of OM (1926 December 15). II. Plastinkoi tonen'koi zhilleta..., no. 334: copy in hand of NM (1926 December). III. fragment of no. 297 (from line "Semipalatnye prostory...": copy in hand of NM (undated). IV. Plastinkoi tonen'koi zhilleta..., no. 334;, 1926 December 15-27, on obverse of sheet: Sosnovoi roshchitsy zakon..., no. 333: both in hand of NM, 1926 December 16-17 (1926 December 15-27) (1926 December 16-17). V. letter from NM to E. Ia. Khazin 1926 December 19, contains: no. 297 and no. 333, 1926 December 15, 1926 December 16 (1926 December 19) (1926 December 15) (1926 December 16) -- 69. Sosnovoi roshchitsy zakon..., no. 335: copy in hand of NM, date in hand of OM (1926 December 16-18) -- 70. Eta oblast' v temnovod'e..., no. 338 (1926 December). I. final manuscript in hand of NM, corrections and date in hand of OM verso (1926 December 24). II. fragment of Plastinkoi tonenkoi Zhiletta, no. 354, in hand of MN (undated). III. copy in hand of NM (1926 December). IV-V. "Shlo tsepochkoi v temnovod'e...", no. 339 (variant of no. 338): 2 copies in hand of NM, both dated, same date (1926 December 26). VI-VII. "Noch. Doroga. Son pervichnyi...," variant of no. 338: 3 copies in hand of NM, one dated (1926 December 23-25). VIII-IX. "Gde ia? Chto so mnoi durnogo?" variant of no. 338, 2 copies in hand of NM, one dated (1926 December 23-25) -- 71.[ Vekhi dal'nego oboza...], no. 340: copy in hand of N. Shtempel', date in hand of OM (1926 December 26) -- 72. Kak podarok zapozdalyi..., no. 336: copy in hand of NM (1926 December 29-30) -- 73. Ottogo vse neudachi..., no. 337 (undated). I. typed copy (undated). II. two copies in hand of NM (1926 December 29-30) -- 74. Tvoi zrachek v nebesnoi korke..., no. 345 (1937 January 2-February 2). I. copy in hand of NM (1937 January 2). II. copy in hand of NM, date in hand OM; according to NM, OM's date is incorrect (note by I. Semenko) (1937 February 2) -- 75. Ulybnis', iagnenok gnevnyi s rafaeleva kholsta..., no. no. 321 (1937 January). I. copy in hand of NM (1937 January 9). II. copy in hand of NM (1937 January) -- 76. Kogda v vetviakh ponurykh..., no. 344 (1937 January 9-10). I. copy in hand of N. Shtempel', date in hand of OM (1937 January 9). II. copy in hand of NM (1937 January 9-10) -- 77. Drozhzhi mira dorogie..., no. 346-347 (1937 January 12-18). I. no. 346: copy in hand of NM, date in hand of OM (1937 January 12). II. no. 346: copy of first two stanzas in hand of NM, date in hand of OM (1937 January 12-14). III. no. 347: copy in hand of NM (1937 January 12-18). IV. no. 347: typed copy (1937 January 12-18) -- 78. Vlez besenok v mokroi sherstke..., no. 348 (1937 January 12-18). I. copy in hand of NM (1937 January 12-18). II. typed copy, date in hand of NM (1937 January 18) -- 79. [ Eshche ne umer ty, eshche ty ne odin...], no. 354: copy of last two stanzas (1937 January 15-16) -- 80. V litso morozu ia gliazhu odin..., no. 349: copy in hand of NM (1937 January 16) -- 81. O, etot medlennyi, odyshlivyi prostor!..., no. 313: copy in hand of NM (1937 January 16) -- 82. Ne sravnivai: zhivushchii nesravnim..., no. 317: typed copy (undated) -- 83. Kak zhenstvennoe serebro gorit..., no. 353; copy in hand of NM (undated) -- 84. Ia nynche v pautine svetovoi..., no. 355 (1937 January 19). I. copy in hand of NM (1937 January 19). II. typed copy (undated) -- 85. Kak zemliu gde-nibud' nebesnyi kamen' budit..., no. 357 (1937 January 20). I. copy in hand of NM (1937 January 20). II. typed copy (1937 January 20) -- 86. Slyshu, slyshu rannii led..., no. 358 (1937 January 21-22). I. short variant, copy in hand of NM (1937 January 21). II. full variant (1937 January 22) -- 87. Liubliu moroznoe dykhan'e..., no. 359: copy in hand of NM (1937 January 24) -- 88. Kuda mne detsia v etom ianvare..., no. 360: copy in hand of NM (1937 February) -- 89. Kak svetoteni muchennik Rembrandt..., no. 369 (1937 February). I. copy in hand of NM verso (1937 February). II. Eshche on pomnit bashmakov iznos...., no. 363, 2 stanzas and two lines in hand of NM (undated). III. final manuscript in hand of NM (blue ink) (1937 February 4) -- 90. Razryvy kruglykh bukht i khriashch i sineva..., no. 366: copy in hand of NM (1937 February 4) -- 91. Gde sviazannyi i prigvozhdennyi ston..., no. 356 (1937 January 19-February). I. copy in hand of NM (1937 February). II. final manuscript in hand of NM (blue ink) (1937 January 19-February 4). III. typed copy (1937 February) -- 92. Kak derevo i med' --Favorskogo polet..., no. 369 (1937 February). I. copy in hand of NM (1937 February). II. typed copy (1937 February) -- 93. Oboroniaet son svoiu donskuiu son'..., no. 371 (1937 January 18-February). I. author's draft manuscript (1937 February 3). II. (on reverse of I.): first manuscript of final variant in hand of NM ("Ukhodiat vdal' liudskikh golov bugry..."), last stanza in hand of OM (1937 January 18-February 3). III. copy of final version in hand of NM (undated). IV. typed copy of above, cut in half, text crossed out (1937 February) -- 94. Sred' narodnogo shuma i spekha..., no. 361: copy in hand of NM (1937) -- 95. Vooruzhennyi zren'em uzkikh os..., no. 346: copy in hand of NM (1937 February) -- 96. Poiu, kogda gortan' syra, dusha sukha..., no. 327: copy in hand of NM (1937 February) -- 97. Byli ochi ostree tochimoi kosy..., no. 368: copy in hand of NM (1937 February) -- 98. Eshche on pomnit bashmakov iznos..., no. 363: typed copy (1937 February 7-11) -- 99. Ia v l'vinyi rov i v krepost' pogruzhen..., no. 370 (1937 February). I. copy in hand of NM (1937 February). II. copy in hand of NM (1937 February 12) -- 100. Esli b menia nashi vragi vziali..., no. 372 (1937 February). I. copy in hand of NM (up to fourth line from end) (1937 February). II. typed copy, cut in half (1937 February) -- 101. Ia moliu, kak zhalosti i milosti..., ( Ia proshu, kak zhalosti i milosti... ) no. 373 (1937 March 3). I. copy in hand of NM (1937 March 3). II. copy in hand of NM (1937 March 3). III. typed copy (1937 March 3) -- 102. Na doske malinovoi, chervonnoi, no. 341: copy in hand of NM (1937 March 6) -- 103. Ia videl ozero stoiavshee otvesno..., no. 379 (1937 March 4). I. author's final manuscript, title: Reims-Laon (1937 March 4). II. copy in hand of NM (1937 March 4) -- 104. Stikhi o neizvestnom soldate, no. 362 (1937-1969). I. author's manuscript (1937 March 3). II. copy in hand of NM made in 1930s (OM's lifetime -- I. Semenko) (1937 March 9-10). III. copy of fragment in hand of NM (undated). IV. fragment ("Skvoz' efir desiatichno oznachennyi...") in hand of NM, paper and style of hadwriting identical to copy of fragment in A. Belomu cycle (items 45-48)(I. Semenko) V-VI. fragments in hand of NM (undated). VII. copy in hand of NM: pages from "Al'bom no. 1" made in OM's lifetime (important for establishing principal text -- I. Semenko) (1937) Note: On same sheets: copies of Esli b menia nashi vragi vziali..., Kak po ulitsam Kieva-viia..., Ia skazhu eto nacherno, shopotom..., Rim (Gde liagushki...) Zabludilsia ia v nebe: chto delat'? (2 variants), O, kak zhe ia khochu..., Mozhet byt' eto tochka bezumiia... (no. no. 372, 361, 376, 381, 378-379, 384, 346 resp.).. VIII. fragments in NM's hand: attempts to reconstruct the poem by memory 1950s-1960s when m